A Guide to the Howard S. Avery Papers, 1913-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Howard S. Avery Papers, 1913-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Avery, Howard S. (Howard Shaeffer), 1906-1996
Ms1997-026
12.4 Cubic Feet 10 boxes
Howard S. Avery graduated from Virginia Tech in 1927 with a B.S. in Mining and Engineering. He worked for the American Brake Shoe Company, later known as the Abex Corporation, as a research metallurgist from 1935 to 1971. The collection consists of Avery's personal papers and photographs related to his student days at Virginia Tech, including photos taken mainly in 1927 while Avery was the photographic editor of the Bugle yearbook. This collection also includes personal papers, correspondence, brochures, and other materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Howard S. Avery Papers were donated to the Special Collections in 1996.
Biographical Information
Howard S. Avery was born in Canon City, Colorado in 1906. His family moved to Virginia when he was eleven, and he attended high school in Roanoke and college in Blacksburg. He received a B.S. in Mining & Engineering in 1927 and an Engineer of Mines degree with honors in 1928, both from Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Avery was very active during his student days at VPI. He was a member of the track team, the rifle club, the radio club, and the boxing club. In 1927 he served as the photographic editor of the Bugle yearbook. He was married in 1935 to Louise Steele and had four children.
Following several years of mining engineering and geology work in Mexico, steel mill experience, and teaching, he joined the newly organized Metallurgical Department of the American Brake Shoe Company, now the Abex Corporation, located in Mahwah, New Jersey in 1934. He is identified with this company's research in various aspects of industrial wear. As a research metallurgist his duties involved planning and supervising research and development of alloys to resist heat, abrasion and impact. He became internationally known in the field of metallurgy, conducting pioneering work in the areas of precise creep-rupture testing, thermal fatigue evaluation, and carburizing behavior. Two of his technical papers garnered Lincoln Gold Medal awards, and he received the first Award of the New York Chapter of the American Society of Metals. He also contributed to several engineering handbooks, was issued a number of patents, and is the author of several dozen technical papers. His career at the Abex Corporation lasted until 1971.
Professional affiliations outside the Abex Corporation include the American Welding Society, The American Society for Metals, the Metal Science Club, The American Institute of Mining and Metallurgical Engineers, The American Society for Quality Control, and the British Iron and Steel Institute. Avery also had a wide range of outside interests and participated in activities that included training Boy Scout leaders, supervision of a junior rifle club, operating an amateur radio station W2HBH, and service on the Mahwah, New Jersey Board of Education and as a Civil Defense Director. Howard Avery passed away in August 1996 in Roanoke, VA.
Scope and Content
The Howard S. Avery Papers contain correspondence, brochures, journals and photographs from Avery's student days at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI) as well as an assortment of his professional and personal papers amassed from the years 1922 to 1995.
The collection is comprised of memorabilia from his years at VPI, including an extensive photograph collection that illustrates student life. The collection also contains notebooks of class notes and journals of scouting trips that give extensive information on the geology of southwest Virginia. The collection contains a VPI psalm book from 1924, a program of the dedication of War Memorial Hall in 1926, and several original layout pages from the 1927 Bugle.
Howard Avery's personal papers contain professional correspondence, brochures, newspaper clippings, and National Rifle Association (NRA) legislation actions in which he participated. It also includes correspondence, brochures, and related documents from the Boy Scouts, the Virginia Tech Alumni Association, the Sierra Club, and other organizations he was involved in during his lifetime.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series divided by subject matter, Personal and Professional Papers and VPI Student Years, each of which has four subseries divided by format of material.
Series I: Personal and Professional Papers, 1913-1996, consists of materials collected and created by Avery during his professional career. There are also documents relating to his hobbies. The series is arranged into three subseries: A. Documents, B. Photos, C. Journals, and D. Artifacts.
Series II: VPI Student Papers, 1923-1928, consists of records created while Avery was a student attending VPI, including schoolwork and extracurricular activities. The series is arranged into three subseries: A. Documents, B. Photos, C. Journals, and D. Artifacts.
Index Terms
Persons:
Avery, Howard S. (Howard Shaeffer), 1906-1996
Corporate Names:
American Brake Shoe Company
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Science and Technology; University Archives
Contents List
- Personal and Professional Papers 1913-1996
  - Documents, 1913-1996
    Scope and Contents
    These documents include personal correspondence, bulletins, newspaper clippings, U.S. Military Regulations, U.S. Army Corps of Engineering, NRA information, Rifle Club correspondence, Boy Scouts manuals, and miscellaneous professional societies membership booklets.
    Arrangement note
    This subseries is grouped together by the subject of the material (such as personal information, professional documents, military documents, NRA), and is chronological within each grouping.
    - Personal Information and Materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1920-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Christmas Cards, 1933-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Materials from Mexico (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Professional Correspondence, 1932-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Metallurgy, 1944-1945, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Abex News, Retirement announcement, July - August 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - U.S. Army Regulations, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National Roster of Scientific and Specialized Personnel, 1945, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Military Projects - American Brake Shoe Co., 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Military and Selective Service Materials, c.1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fort Humphreys, Maps and Materials, Summer 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Fort Humphreys, Training Exercises, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Army Engineering Correspondence Course
      - Materials (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Subcourse 20-1, December 1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Subcourse 20-2, December 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Subcourse 20-6, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Military Correspondence, Officer Reserve Corps, March 1932 - October 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Science 11 - Educational Hygiene Lesson (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Reserve Officer Associations - Roanoke, VA chapter, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - National Rifle Association - Junior Division (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - NRA booklets and clippings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - NRA Legislation Correspondence, 1935-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - NRA Whittington Center, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Firearms Clubs and Organizations - Correspondence, 1935-1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Rifle Club Materials, 1951-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Remington Peters, Shooting Instructor Bulletin (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Firearms Clubs and Organizations - Junior Rifle Tournament Materials (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Boy Scouts, 1932-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Boy Scouts, Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Roanoke Scout Notes, Troop 17, Spring 1933 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Royal Astronomical Society of Canada (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Iron and Steel Institute, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - American Society for Metals, National Engineers Register of Engineers, and O'Connor Research Center (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - American Institute of Mining Metallurgical and Petroleum Engineers, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - American Welding Society, 1950-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Sierra Club correspondence, 1966-1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - American Geographical Society correspondence (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Amateur Radio Materials, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Metallurgy and Engineering Education Materials, 1944-1966 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Engineering Education Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Industrial Arts Education Program, 1932-1960 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - High School speaking engagements, 1948, 1955, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Applications of Metallurgical Microscopy (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Department of Interior Reports - Bureau of Mines Black Powder Study, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Sporting Goods, Clothing and Books Catalogs - Roanoke, VA, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Advertisement Cards, Arcos Company (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Operations Manual for Portable Tape Recorder, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Maps (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - VPI Calendar, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - VPI Alumni Association, 1926-1949 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - VPI Alumni Association Materials (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Sounds from Virginia Tech LP, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Bulletin - Important Facts on State Supported Colleges (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - VPI Memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Invoices from Virginia Photo Finishing Co. and Roanoke Cycle Co., 1925-1927 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1927-1987
    These photographic prints and negatives include unidentified personal shots as well as photos taken in conjunction with his profession.
    The subseries is organized by material type, personal photographs of family and various locations, as well as photographs taken in a professional capacity. For most photographs the date is unknown.
    - Scenes Unidentified, Negatives, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Griffith Industries, Negatives, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Maynard Industries, Welding Negatives, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Slide POS film wear (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Unidentified Negatives (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - 47 Cottage Grove (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous Railroad Crossings (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified Negatives (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Walkerton Industries, Maynard Industries (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Framed Portrait of H. S. Avery (Box 3)
    - Framed Portrait William B. Given Jr., Founder of the American Brake Shoe Company, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Personal Photos, H. S. Avery, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Personal Photos, Unidentified, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Personal Photos, Scenic, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Finished Thesis Work, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Scenes, Unidentified, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
    - Griffith Industries, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Tractor Wear information, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Visit U.S. Bureau of Mines, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Unidentified Rock Samples, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Staffer Chemical Company (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Caracas and Vicinity (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Photo, Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Modern Railroad Crossing, Odin, Illinois (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Taylor-Wharton/Abex Conference (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Foundry Shots (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Maynard Industries (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Journals, 1913-1936
    - U.S. Army Training Regulations Booklet, 1922-1931 (Box 3)
    - The Soldier's Handbook for Use in the Army of the United States, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Manual of First Aid Instruction for Miners, and Mercurochrome in First Aid, 1922, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Geology, Southeast of Roanoke, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Notebook, Journal of travel notes, 1928-1930 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Notes on thesis, Geology around Roanoke, c.1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - USGS Maps for field work, Roanoke and Christiansburg, c.1929 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Maps, measuring tools, notebook for fieldwork, c.1932 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Mine Examination and Geological Field Work, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Notebook, Hikes Around Roanoke, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Iron and Steel Institute Handbook No. 1, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Address List, American Brake Shoe Company, March 1946 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Address List, Metallurgical Department Personnel, c.1936 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Address List of Executives, Officials and Representatives of the American Brake Shoe and Foundry Company and Associated and Subsidiary Companies (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - LeFax Data Sheets on Mining Methods, Metal Stoping (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - S-Curves of Austenite Transformation (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Notes on mapping and geology in the vicinity of Roanoke, VA (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Society of American Military Engineers, Aims and Activities, and TAM Division National Lead Company, Steels for Nuclear Reactors, 1931, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - American Institute of Mining and Metallurgy Engineers, Aims and Activities, c.1925 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Artifacts
    - Official Leggings of the Boy Scouts of America (Box 6)
    - 305th Engineers Hat (Box 6)
    - U.S. Army pennant (Box 7)
    - Blue and white tie (Box 7)
    - VMI Armband (Box 7)
- VPI Student Years, 1923-1928, 1980
  - Documents, 1923-1928, 1980
    This subseries includes documents created and collected by Howard Avery while attending Virginia Polytechnic Institute. The documents consist of course work, class assignments, newspaper clippings and VPI memorabilia.
    The documents are arranged chronologically.
    - VPI Psalm Book or A Military Life in Comic, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chemistry Lab Notebook, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Freshman Chemistry Notes, Third Term, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chemistry Exercises, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chemistry Lab Tests, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Class Assignments, Analytics, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Writing Exercises, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Physics Course Notes, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Football Team, Bugle Page, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - R.O.T.C. Materials, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Physics 212 Outline and Notes, c.1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Physics 232 Outline and Notes, c.1925 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Physics Lab Reports, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Regulations of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Clippings, VPI Athletics, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Program for Dedication of the World War Memorial Hall and the Miles Stadium, October 1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Electrical Engineering Lab Report, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Official Program for University of Richmond Fourth Annual South-Atlantic Track Meet, May 1927 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Public Speaking essay, "The Dependence of the United States on Foreign Mineral Resources" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Program for 1927 Rally at VPI, including The Vocational Agricultural High School Contest, the Little International Livestock Show, the Virigina Tech Dairy Show, and a meeting of the Future Farmers of Virginia, April 1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Issue of The Athletic Journal, January 1928 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Geological Columnar Section for Pocahontas Folio, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - VPI Sophomore Pranks, letters to Giles Syndor, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Cerro De Pasco District, copied from Mineral Deposits of South America by Miller and Singewald, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Metal items made in VPI Forge Class, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Freshman Engineering Drawings, 1923 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1924-1927
    This subseries contains photographic prints and negatives of images created by Howard Avery while a student at VPI. Most of the photographs were taken while he was the Photographic Editor of the 1927 Bugle.
    Materials are grouped in three divisions: cadet photographs, athletic photographs and personal photographs. Larger format prints precede the smaller photos. There are also eight photo albums that contain pictures of campus life and trips to surrounding areas.
    - Athletic Teams, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - War Memorial Gym, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Cadet Formation at Athletic Event, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Cadet Companies, Unidentified, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Cadets at Play, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Graduation at War Memorial Gym (interior view), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Father and Son Banquet, YMCA, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified Swimmers, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - VPI Senior H.S. Avery, Negatives, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Col. Deem Inspection, Negatives, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Cadets, Unidentified negatives, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Unidentified VPI Groups, Negatives (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Unidentified campus scenes, Negatives (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified Woman, negative, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Engineer ROTC Camp, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Rats on parade, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - VPI Cadets and campus (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Campus life, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Campus scenes, unidentified individuals (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Roanoke College football game, 1927 Bugle (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - VPI Spring track season, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - VPI Campus life, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "B" Company Officers, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Rats on parade, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Cadets parade in town, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Cadets with artillery, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Cadets at class, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Cadets at play, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Cadet Corps commandant with staff, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Cadet formation inspection, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Cadet equipment inspection, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Cadet companies, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Cadet brass ensemble, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Cadet formation at athletic event, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Cadet dress uniform parade, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Individual Cadets, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Cadet Individuals, Names listed on envelope, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Bugle elections, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Athletic managers, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Baseball team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Baseball games, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Boxing team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Football team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Football games, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 23-26)
    - Rifle team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Drama club, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Tennis team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Track team, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Track team, individuals, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Track and field meets, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Wrestling, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Horticulture exhibit, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - VPI Banquet, interior of Solitude (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Initiation into Monogram Club (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Campus buildings, interiors, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Campus buildings, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Campus scenes (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
  - Journals, 1923-1927
    - Students Handbook of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Compliments of the YMCA, Volume 28, 1923-1924 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Boy Scout Diary, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, Metallurgy class, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Notebook, DAM Geology personnel and VPI addresses, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute in the World War, VPI Bulletin Vol. XXI, No. 1, November 1927 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Notebook, finances, class notes, photography notes, c.1927 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notebook, Economics (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notebook, Petrography (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Artifacts, 1923-1926
    - VPI Cadet Cord (Box 6)
    - VPI Cadet Hat (Box 6)
    - Va Tech pennant (Box 7)
    - VPI belt buckles, 3 (Box 8)
    - VPI belts, 2 (Box 8)
    - VPI buttons with Virginia state seal, 11 (Box 8)
    - VPI sweater (Box 9)
    - VPI pennant, 1927 (Box 9)
    - VPI paddle (Box 9)
    - VPI Cadet uniform, jacket and pants, c.1923-1926 (Box 10)
    - VPI Football uniform, pants only, c.1923-1926 (Box 10)